Guide to the Patrick H. Cain papers, 1783-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Patrick H. Cain papers 1783-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Cain, Patrick H.
3.5 Linear Feet Approx. 2,904 Items
Merchant, tobacco merchant, landowner, distiller, and State Representative, from Mocksville and Settle (Davie Co.), N.C.
Personal, legal, business, and financial papers of Patrick H. Cain and the Cain family, from Davie County, N.C. Included are letters describing life and social customs in Georgia; the education of women; student life at Normal College (later Trinity College, then Duke University) and at the University of North Carolina; Western migration; prices of products and services, the value of slaves, and the wages of freedmen; and the life of Confederate soldiers and military actions at First Manassas and Gettysburg. Legal papers consist of land grants, deeds, mortgages, arrests and summonses for debts, promissory notes, and material relating to the administration of various estates. Financial records include tax receipts and accounts. There is one volume of patient accounts, 1906-1925, belonging to Dr. John Cain. Correspondents include George Burgess Anderson, Francis Asbury, Samuel Ashe, Kemp P. Battle, John Joseph Bruner, D. R. Bruton, Lyman Copeland Draper, David Moffatt Furches, William H. Hayes, William Hill, Hamilton C. Jones, Leonidas Polk, Zebulon Vance, and Jonathan Worth.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Patrick H. Cain Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1957.
Biographical Note
Patrick H. Cain was born in 1815 in Davie County, N.C., the son of Daniel Cain and Elizabeth Hutchins. Patrick Cain married Susan Wilder Cheshire and had the following children: William Gaston, John Manley, Betty Ann, Millard Fillmore, Robert Lee.
Collection Overview
Personal, legal, business, and financial papers of the Cain family. Included are letters describing life and social customs in Georgia, 1824-1827; school life at girls' academies, 1843-1856, at Normal College (later Trinity College), 1855-1856, at a seminary, 1869, and at the University of North Carolina, 1871-1880; Western migration and Western lands; business methods; prices of products and services, the value of slaves, and wages and tenancy of freedmen; the life of Confederate soldiers, including accounts of military activities, especially First Manassas and Gettysburg, and comments on conditions in the army and on officers, Jefferson Davis, and Abraham Lincoln.
Legal papers consist of land grants, deeds, mortgages, arrests and summonses for debts, promissory notes, and material relating to the administration of various estates. There are broadsides concerning Jonathan Worth and W. W. Holden. Financial records consist of tax receipts; accounts, 1889-1895, kept in advertising booklets; and a ledger containing patient accounts, 1906-1925, belonging to Dr. John M. Cain, Patrick Cain's brother. There are many manuscript volumes in the collection, chiefly financial.
Correspondents include George Burgess Anderson, Francis Asbury, Samuel Ashe, Kemp P. Battle, John Joseph Bruner, D. R. Bruton, Lyman Copeland Draper, David Moffatt Furches, Will H. Hayes, William Hill, Hamilton C. Jones, Leonidas Polk, Zebulon Vance, and Jonathan Worth.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cain, Patrick H.
Cain family
Draper, Lyman Copeland, 1815-1891
Polk, Leonidas, 1806-1864
Vance, Zebulon Baird, 1830-1894
Worth, Jonathan, 1802-1869
Asbury, Francis, 1745-1816
Battle, Kemp P. (Kemp Plummer), 1831-1919
Normal College (Randolph County, N.C.)
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Social conditions
Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Va., 1861
Freedmen -- North Carolina
Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863
Migration, Internal -- United States
Merchants -- Accounting
Merchants -- North Carolina
Probate law and practice -- North Carolina
Slave trade -- North Carolina
Slavery -- North Carolina
Universities and colleges -- North Carolina
Women -- Education -- North Carolina
Davie County (N.C.) -- Commerce
Southern States -- Economic conditions
Georgia -- Social life and customs
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Daybook
Related Material
Last Will and Testament of Daniel Cain of Davie County, NC, 1844, 1849 [Patrick Cain was the executor; contains names of slaves]
NC State Archives, Raleigh, N.C.
Contents of Collection
- Patrick H. Cain papers, 1783-1940, (8 boxes)
  Titles of series were taken from box labels.
  - Letters
    - 1824-1912, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1913-1940 (Box 2)
  - Legal Papers
    - 1783-1856, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1857-1924, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Bills, Receipts
    - 1811-1850s, (5 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1860s-1890s, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1900-1940, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany and Printed Material (Box 6)
  - Volumes, (approximately 24) (Box 7)
  - Volumes (Box 8)
  - Bound manuscript volume (Box F:6868)